All right, we'll call it a regular scheduled meeting of my
city council from Monday, July 1st, 2024.
But the input, let's go to personal passes.
We've got none.
Three times less, much to do.
So I can.
He's set by.
Fittman.
Hi.
Don't go.
Parker.
Hi.
Four.
Claims less for any.
O.
Concrete.
Much to approve.
Sign up.
He's set by.
Don't go.
Fittman.
Who's then?
Parker.
Five.
Five minutes from the June.
17, 20, 24, regular meeting in the June 24th, 2024, special meeting.
Most of the proof.
Time.
He's set by.
Don't go.
Hi.
Fittman.
Parker.
Five.
Discussion, possible action.
Lead agency application and plans for the community change grant.
And upcoming movie and Riverview Park.
Mr. Buckejim.
And Martin looks like.
All right.
As some of you know, we have a plot.
We are in the process of putting together an application for a community change grant from the EPA.
This would be a $10,000,000,000,000 investment for our community.
The purpose of the grant is really to meet three goals.
Right.
Let me back up first.
I can't.
What we're.
What we're looking to do, where we have a meeting scheduled with Tyler and Ben tomorrow.
And we'll be talking more about the details and mechanics of this.
I don't know if this will have to go before the city council for a formal vote and approval.
So we're not asking for any vote today.
But what we want to do today is give you an overview of what this great proposal is.
What the city's involvement could be if the city wants to be involved and to take questions and engage in a discussion that you folks may have.
So what is this grant?
What's it about?
The grant looks to do three things.
Every successful application has to do three things.
First, it has to protect against pollution and exposure to pollution.
Right.
So here that obviously is flooding.
It's dark creek.
Second, it has to mitigate against the effects of climate change in some way.
And so again, that speaks to flooding and flooding preparedness.
The third is, and this is the magic sauce in this grant.
It has to provide other community benefits.
So if we built a burn to prevent dark creek from flooding myama,
that would achieve the first two objectives.
But it doesn't do anything else for our community.
What EPA wants to do is they want to provide large amounts of money to help communities transform themselves.
They want to build big, build big things in communities, and it has to be built and finished within three years.
They want to build big things in communities that will catalyze future growth, future development in really powerful ways.
So, what's the proposal that we are looking at?
We are looking at no real opportunities close by to get close to nature in a space that is safe that doesn't look and feel like your typical city park.
People want to hike, you want to go for a hike, where do you go? You drive up to Joplin, you go to Shull Creek.
Beyond that, you're looking at, and there are the trails over near the reporter course.
Beyond that, you're looking at Arkansas. You're looking at driving at least an hour, maybe two hours, maybe three hours.
Well, this grant says, hey, we could bring that here. We could create something like that here, and the opportunity is where we view park.
So, we're not going to go over each and every slide, you will have digital copies of them, but we are going to hit sort of five points here and we're back into you want to take it from here.
So, if we were looking at just the basics of what we could do, we could dream small. We could imagine doing something on this side of the river, just like it is, and change the early part of the park into a tall grass, and I know we've already got some of that happening in this community.
And the other pollinator gardens that is drowning his provided the city.
But we're looking to create these trails that could be moe differently. You could have a different route through the park next year, and the year after you could change it every year.
That park could be that part of the park would be burned to maintain it every few years to make sure that these tall grass grow as they should in our maintain well.
Then the other part of the park is the forest, and I know some of you have wandered down there.
It's absolutely magical.
You already have a forest.
Why not be enjoyed?
Why not create trails that would go to it?
And with this first vision, you would walk through the park,
you would walk down into the forest.
And you could connect to the future trail
that the Ottawa County is putting in,
you're hoping to put it.
It would have overlooked platforms.
And we've got some images over here
of what some of those platforms might look like.
And again, the fishing pierce and the other ways
to access the river.
I like this, but I want more.
And I want us to dream bigger.
And we, through some imagining, with some of the city
officials, perhaps one day the established ball parks
we moved, because in a flood, they're hard to clean now.
So perhaps they could be moved.
And perhaps there's where they were.
Maybe you would have soccer fields.
It would be easily maintained in a flood.
But that tall grass Perry, otherwise,
could continue to grow.
And in this one, you see mounds.
And this is the really Ottawa County
is the home for six tribes that had mounds in their culture.
They built mounds that are now, like in Ohio,
world heritage sites.
These tribes here came from a long history
and a culture connected with mounds.
Perhaps this could incorporate some of that into this park,
along this riverfront.
You really can't tell by this image.
But we're imagining banks that are stabilized
so that you have rows of seating are sitting.
And then another row below.
So you've got access to fish, or to sit, and watch the river.
Where we really have very little access.
I mean, we can stand up at the edge, but that's about all you can do,
or maybe step down and sit on the steps, if you want.
But very little.
And then imagine, with us, we expand and we go across the river.
And we have the park grow to include maybe it's the other disk golf course that we lost.
Maybe that's over there.
Maybe there's trails for the horses.
Maybe there's another way we enjoy that part of the park.
And how do we get there?
We're imagining a pedestrian bridge over to the other side of the river.
There's a much expanded walkway in the forest so that maybe you only want to one mile walk.
Maybe you want it along the walk, so you can do loops there.
If you want to, you can imagine with us what some of those facilities could look like.
So when we met a couple of weeks ago, we put the floodplain managers in the room with
us and tuned in Oklahoma Water Resources Board to figure out what do you think?
Can we do a thing like this?
And they said, well, you know, you just need some permits.
Well, with this grant, we've got the money to do the permits, we've got, we believe the time
to do it.
Another piece and what's really exciting about this grant is when the landscape designers were
providing us with technical assistance to make all of the maintenance of the right.
And these are proposals.
These are ideas.
This is not a final design proposal.
This is what goes in our application to say, here's our vision, right.
And what actually gets built will probably be different in some, but one of the things that really
came up with landscape desires when they were in town is that we have so many people who want
to get around by foot or by bicycle, or we have to get around by foot or by bicycle, but
we don't have much signage, we have all these places where people need to get, we've got schools
in town, we've got parks in town, grocery stores, we have NEO, A&M, college, sites that are
important for our community, you know, the old B of good rich place, knows what's going to
have.
We have opportunity, maybe, and so this part of the proposal could possibly be part
of this grant action, making...
signed by trails or paths, right?
There may be more involved permitting issues
with making this happen.
So this may not be possible to achieve within three years.
But what's really exciting is that they went
in the trouble of designing an exhibition.
And if something like this were something
that the community wants to pursue in the future,
but it can't be done in three years,
because that's the requirement of this grant
to do in three years in your dark, right?
Who we have this, that we use in a later grant application
to fund something like that.
And that is part of the point of this grant
is to catalyze not just this project,
but for this to become a spring or less.
So that's one piece.
Another is sign.
And here I'll say we already have a five-year commitment
from the National Park Service to provide us
with technical assistance
for making different kinds of signage.
And that is an integral, if we get this community
to create with this project.
So we have tremendous history here.
We have the history of folks who work to be at good rich.
We have the history of mining.
I mean, you think about all the interesting history
that's going on in some local Facebook groups, right?
Where people are really sharing local history.
We can commemorate that public sign.
We can recognize our unique ecology.
The nature that we have is important that this community, I think,
learned to reconnect and we've got.
And so we can show signage about local birds,
about local plants, in places where you're going
to find that including a long parkour,
and that's the other thing we need to establish.
This says that anything around here is
littered outside the repository on these 40 road south of the pitch.
That is the only permanently installed signage work.
Now we don't need to blast it everywhere.
But a long parkour, where kids are swimming,
we need permits.
We need signs that with children in mining.
And so that is part of rendering of what
what's the mountains and so on.
But we've been staying for like all of this design instead of pretending so as to lay that hello be the response
Millions city the city would chiefly the lead app can take the money and manage this band is so large and I would say
I mean putting my formal orders hat on for a second
You know the city would have to hire someone just to manage this because all the money spent has to follow federal
And this grant contemplates when we get to the money hiring a full-time person to manage it a full-time project manager
Right bookkeeper
That's all built into the contemplated budget for this so they go with me that while the city would be responsible for managing the money
You would have to oversee those people you wouldn't have to task your current bookkeeper's to manage this money
Right that you don't have to have a really shoot me hats on staff don't place that word on it
But chiefly managed money, but also you would put the city in the position of having a great deal of say over how the decisions are made in the city property
Right, you know the city owns it and so as the person managing the product manager you folks would be in the position that we have to
So I need to back up. We will have a letter agreement that lays out everybody's responsibility
So we would be the statutory department city would be the letter laying that out will spell every single thing out
That's what we speak with Tom and there are templates out there. We don't have to admit this from the law
There are templates out there
The folks were helping us with the application
They're working with
The chiefly is a matter of money
possible for the city probably has more experience managing larger grants than we do.
Thoughts are concerned from Vanderbilt.
We're seeing all of this gives us an introduction to our conversation tomorrow.
So do you guys have them at pretty much film?
Yes, I'll brief presentation on it.
I've talked with Martin about you didn't see you in the press.
I was focused on the land version question.
So it says the discussion of possible action.
No actual action.
I'd like to share with you also the fact that as a nonprofit, this grant can't be given just to a city.
It has to have a partner that's a nonprofit.
And we were approached to apply for the technical assistance for this and we received it.
It was a $200,000 grant that brought us no money, but it brought us the architects.
Here, to visit with the community and get our concerns and go back and design a project that could meet some of our needs.
And what I see with this project is hope.
And I know when you see me come in the door, you go, oh no, what's wrong with that?
I know it, but this could bring us all joy and hope for a new change.
It is a change grant.
And one that I believe the city deserves to have.
And whatever we can do to make the application as strong as we can, we will.
We believe that this city deserves a change.
So long term, say it's all put in and it's functional.
It can be used daily.
Who maintains the, everything, who maintains the cleans it, change out the boards.
So that is part of what we have to figure out, because that part of the application is main change.
And we get to decide that together, what commonly will happen in grants like this is the city might give what's considered sort of wondering if the rights of you want to change for them.
What are the trails going to all respiratory
and low at different lengths of pride?
If there's something unusual that needs to be done,
that might fall on this category,
far from the non-profit organization, right?
But we get to figure that out together.
We get to define how we want that to work
and what each of us thinks we can do.
What I will say is that this is really designed to be as low
maintenance as possible.
So that's why using composite materials and simple
at the core pride is much, much more durable.
It's not hair or waterway.
So yeah, I mean, those are things that we're out of.
And we will spell out before we apply it.
Was that a copy of the interview with that?
Does that include removing all the sediment off of that?
Nice looking thing when the flood water is reside,
and there's six to eight inches of mud on it.
And that's what we're going to have to talk about.
Is, is, you know, how do we feel with that?
And maybe that will be in part of the design.
I mean, maybe it will be such that there are
there are removal cutouts,
edging for safety, but maybe you remove part of it.
And that's where it gets swept off for a period of it.
But yeah, I mean, those are all things that we have to look after
to figure out.
And the first step that we get this right is going to be bringing in
an actual engineering platform to do the real real design,
which will begin to address some of those specific concerns.
How do we wash this off?
We know we're going to have to pick them on.
How do we get it off?
Do we need to be able to support tiny little front end loader that can just scrape it?
Like, it's a little black hole?
You know, what do we need?
So yeah, I mean, great question.
I don't know if you need to buy it, but that's working together.
Nice when you get that one slide.
And you're soon right talk about the splash pad area.
And you said, never mind, cities already have some plans here.
Yeah, yeah, sorry, you have a question.
So the thing we have planned there is city pool.
Is that something this grant can help with?
It's possible.
Quite possible.
And the really thing is these are just IP,
these are starting points for purposes of getting the app.
If the city is really serious, but the question is,
can you do it three years?
Because that's the thing, this has to be built and done.
Well, the city is two years away from step one.
That might be a challenge.
You've got a mound right where the pool is at,
so for you, you're done in three years.
It'll have to be done in three years.
Yeah, I mean, that's something we definitely talk about.
The verb, they go, this is out.
Thank you.
Then let's talk about the movies.
Oh, I remember.
You thought, you know, there's something else here.
Change a pace.
Yeah, we were able to, well, I think some of you got
to see meet me at the creek, the little film that Lauren Waters did.
Well, she didn't stop there.
She applied for other grants.
One of them was for a pop-up movie theater screen that's 16-foot diameter.
And it pops up.
You air it up.
And with it, the our commitment is to show movies.
And so we would like to show movies at Riverview Park, this summer.
And one evening, and we'll see if it's a hit.
Maybe we'll want to do it more often.
But at least one evening at Riverview Park.
We want to show four little short movies.
One will be meet me at the creek.
Another is Save Our Creek, which is a little film that are summer campers.
And another is the river is me and one other one.
They're very short films.
And yeah, so it would be July 12th.
And start.
We'd hope people would gather about 830.
And we'd love to have you all come.
And in my dream of dreams, I'd like to have a row of boxes with little wheels on it.
And pillows in the boxes for little children to sit in, like the movie theater.
I'd like to drive in.
Anyway, yeah, and we.
With the grant, we also got our own popcorn machine.
So we'll be having popcorn.
And there's no cost.
We're all about the popcorn, right?
So anyway, it's something fun to do this summer.
And we're hoping that you would approve that.
That would actually go through your Kevin.
So far so good.
Thank you.
Well, I'll tell you, I already have a previous engagement on the 12th.
be there. Okay. I don't know about the rest of you guys. Thank Brian as the same engagement
I have actually. Yeah. So, at least that's the Kevin. Yeah. If you, if you want to, we'll
save you a seat. But you better bring your own chair. I might not have a niff bug. Thank you very much.
Thank you. Number seven, a budget member 24, 21, that's 21, city managers, budget,
receding, it's been a $10,561.33, for sales tax incentive, agreement, C, 23, that's 64,
reimburseing 75% of submitted sales tax for five years, or $50,000 whichever comes first,
library receding, and spending $6,444.10 a donations for the specific program indicated.
Emergency management, receding, and spending $4,294 a 30 cents on the insurance for
every money to pay for silent repair. So, this is the first amendment for this fiscal year,
and it's just what you said. It's in three parts. One is to receive an expense, sales tax incentive,
agreement, C, 23, that's 64. That is where the new business got 75% of their sales tax.
And that's going to get that last for either five years or up to $50,000, which ever comes first.
The library is asking to recede in and spend some donations, money, and then emergency management,
wanting to expense, some insurance funds to repair sirens.
Hi.
Hey, annual field lease agreement for the city of my own multi-purpose sports complex on the
annual and in campus with my and with community facilities authority for fiscal year 24, 25.
This is the eighth year of the eighth of agreements we had with MCFA. It allows us the city to use
the stadium for the exact same amount. It gives us the same access to it that in the O and mine of public schools
house. So, they have 10 to 11 good long games. We can have 10 to 11 events.
How many do we usually have?
Well, they're the first we had two or three in that we don't have.
Well, good if we wanted to. If we approve this.
Oh, yeah, eight minus one. That's right. We used to have a J C double A.
I'll make a motion when you approve.
Sit back.
Parker.
Not in ratify city manager's signature on a traveler's authorization to buy and coverage
for fiscal year 2425.
Cindy and Christie.
Yes.
Hey.
We just we would like your approval to ratify the signature for the travelers.
The authorization to buy and coverage for fiscal year 2425.
Anything special?
We are still negotiating to get a lower premium.
So this the numbers that we have on here are going to be a little bit less than what we have on the farm.
Things have changed since.
Right.
Back to us.
So thank you to them for working on it.
Obviously we want to have insurance.
So we signed it.
So we can enjoy first.
We have the policy that they're working on.
So we need to approve this to stay with our insurance.
Okay.
But I mean there are still planning to lower it.
Right.
They've split their commission.
They gave they went from a 15% commission down to 7.5%.
So we're still working on getting all the accurate numbers back.
Motion to approve.
Second.
All right.
Thank you.
Ten.
The new business of any of which is.
We're closing this agenda.
11 staff reports.
12 mayor counsel community announcements.
We talked about the dinner on Main Street.
Then we had.
Jimmy.
Our team.
Thank you.
I'll see you here.
Here.
But they put on the dinner on Main Street.
So 150.
Yeah.
156 seats to that.
Sold out less than 48 hours.
They wouldn't sure how fast it was going to go or how well it's going to go.
And I know there's a lot of people up sick.
They didn't get to come.
But it was learning learning experience.
But they knocked it out of park.
It was a great event.
It was more than just about community.
Really wouldn't have a lot of talking.
And.
And stop it.
Just people busy.
And it was nice meal.
I think they already planned an hour for the fall.
And the.
or should be increased and so everybody have an opportunity to go, but if you get a chance
of the fall, you should go.
That's it.
It was really good to be at.
So, good to go.
So those girls were bringing something new to the community that kind of brought everybody together
around the heart of downtown.
So, so I got, see you, Amanda.
I mean, you can't just have a couple of things.
So, first off, thank you to the board for this opportunity and I today is my first official
day as the city manager, so I know it's a new time I would end up doing meet and greet
and sometimes I'm down the road, so, but thank you, I'm thinking to the board, and that
was my whole best time to go to the city to be the city manager, maybe came a little sooner
than I thought, but here I am.
I want to thank my utility screws.
I mean, there's a bunch of them back there, without them, we would not be as accessible as we are.
So, thank you very much.
We've done a lot of things for the community a lot, and I mean, I appreciate everybody showing up
tonight and showing their support, so I'm going to see it to you, I just think about it, I don't
know how to have emotions or whatever, so, I mean, streets, streets, it's part of the utility
screen, when I say utility streets, it's part of it, Robert's back there, so, thank you guys,
and we've done anywhere from Skita, sub stations, all the streets, all the water lines, it's
just, you know, we've had a huge deal, and then lastly, I want to thank my family, my wife and
daughter here, Tinsley and Ryan, my son couldn't be here tonight, he is with his dad, you know,
my uncle, I've never gone to whatever he became to fire chief, I remember going to that one,
they made in the fire chief, so, my uncle David, he worked here for how many years, they've
had 32 years, and then my mom and dad, I love him to dad, my dad is still not excited about
me doing this job, but my mom says, go for it, but my dad, you know, I think he's still
reserved on it, so, but I'm excited, you know, so, I'm gonna back up, I thought we had to
just later, but I guess I'll miss my family, so my back up to the mayor council time, I'll tell
her, by the way, we went through the process and had 29 applicants for the job, a city manager, we broke
that down to 9, and Tyler was in top of the list, we were married at 9, so, we went through everything
to break those down, and in fact, in that meeting of 9, one of our council, we were people
who were hired to pay, so, why are we wasting our time?
Our guys here, let's just hire him to move on, well, we need to do our due diligence, and we need
to do that for the community, but we need to do it for Tyler as well, because we didn't want
somebody to come back and say we just hand in the job, because he was here, we didn't hand
in the job, because it was easy to do that, we felt like we owed him better than that, so,
we broke it down to 3, again, Tyler was in top, and once we broke it down to 3, one of the
applicants, really the only competition, Tyler had my opinion, people doubt for families, so I believe
I believe what I'm going to say truly, is that God let us win this game.
And we allowed him to dictate what we were doing.
And we just had to follow what he was putting in front of us.
And every time I make him lean back to Tyler.
So Tyler was right guy for this job.
We did our new diligence as a team to make sure
that there wasn't somebody else out there.
He kept wanting to Tyler.
And I'm going to go back and tell a little story
about when we named him interim.
And the first time around when I first got elected mayor,
he had been named the interim about a week before I
took over his mayor.
And Tyler struggled with that the first time around.
He struggled with being the interim.
He didn't want to upset anybody.
He didn't want to hurt anybody's feelings.
And I think it's setting back a little bit that first time around.
And the second time, he impressed the heck out of me,
the maturity and the growth that I see in Tyler was huge
from the first time to the second time.
In fact, he wasn't going to apply.
And I asked him to apply after watching in the interim role.
But I remember the conversation we had in the parking lot out
here and I said, Tyler, he said, I'm going to do better this time around.
So I know you are because I'm going to make sure you do.
And that's the first time around.
You sucked at this.
And you can't suck at this time.
I said, the only thing that saved you was I was a brand new mayor and I sucked at that.
So he's the one who's going to do that this time.
But he really has impressed me and I was at that because we hired the best one period.
And I will have that discussion with anybody that wants to have that discussion out of the
afternoon.
We had we hired the best candidate.
So congratulations Tyler.
I know you're going to do great.
I'm going to say in that, I want to thank his family.
I definitely want to thank his wife because he's going to be gone.
It's an awful death against him.
If you're mad anybody, be mad at Kevin.
I can take it.
You guys think I'll say his name.
I'm sorry.
Okay.
With that, we're going to 14, which is this meeting, we're not going to be continued from the Council
Chambers.
We're going to be in the staff room for the purpose of executive session.
Ethical completion of the agenda item number 6 of the MIPFA.